Guide to the Croft/Wunsch family papers, 1931-2000 MS 752
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Croft/Wunsch family papers
1931-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wunsch, Rochelle Croft
MS 752
4 Linear Feet 5 boxes and 1 folder in map drawer
The Croft/Wunsch family papers include correspondence, awards and citations, photographs, scrapbooks, news clippings, newsletters, meeting minutes, and marketing and event materials that document, primarily, the lives of the Croft and Kaplan families, and to a lesser degree, members of the Wunsch family.
Biographical / Historical
Both Louis Croft and his future wife, Ida Sylvia Kaplan, were born June 23, 1918, in Houston Texas. The two married February 9, 1941. Mr. Croft enlisted in the U.S. Army on February 11, 1942, and served for the duration of World War II. The couple had three children: Harry, Rochelle, and Steven. Louis and Ida Croft died October 25, 1992, and February 23, 2006, repectively. Both are interred at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery in Houston.
Abraham (Abe) Croft -- Louis Croft's younger brother -- was born May 12, 1920, in Houston. He attended Southern Methodist University in Dallas where he was named to the College Football All-America Team in 1944. He was drafted by the Chicago Bears and played in 11 games over the 1944 and 1945 seasons. Abe Croft died December 1, 1972 and is interred at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery in Houston.
Rochelle Faye Croft was born August 7, 1948, in Houston. She married Lee Richard Wunsch on March 25, 1979.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, awards and citations, photographs, scrapbooks, news clippings, newsletters, meeting minutes, and marketing and event materials document, primarily, the lives of the Croft and Kaplan families between the years 1931 and 2000, and the Wunsch family to a lesser degree. Of particular interest are letters written from Ida Kaplan Croft to her husband, Louis, during World War II, as well as numerous photographs spanning sixty years.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in thirteen series as follows:
Series I: Awards, Certificates, and Diplomas; Series II: Books/Scrapbooks; Series III: Correspondence; Series IV: Event Materials; Series V: Financial Materials; Series VI: Marketing Materials; Series VII: Meeting Materials; Series VIII: Memorabilia; Series IX: News Clippings; Series X: Newsletters; Series XI: Oversized Materials; Series XII: Photographic Materials; Series XIII: Speeches
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lee & Rochelle Croft Wunsch donated the material in May 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Social life and customs; World War (1939-1945); Jews and Jewish life; Military
Document Types
personal correspondence; photographs; black-and-white photographs; negatives (photographic); scrapbooks; newsletters; clippings (information artifacts); speeches; awards; certificates; Diplomas; memorabilia
Subjects (Persons)
Wunsch, Rochelle Croft
Subjects (Corporations)
B'nai B'rith. Herzl Lodge No. 608
- Series I: Awards, Certificates, and Diplomas
  - Abe Croft's San Jacinto High School diploma & birth certificate, 1920, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates to/in honor of Ida Kaplan Croft, 1929, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates of Appreciation presented to past presidents of Herzl Lodge #608 between 1938 and 1974, 1985-07-14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mizrachi Women Life Membership certificate presented to Pearl Croft, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates of Appreciation & Membership presented to Louis Croft, 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Achievement Award to Herzl Lodge No. 608 (2), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Plaque plate - "Houston B'nai B'rith Council 1986 Man of the Year presented to Louis Croft", 1986-03-10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Plaque plate - Ida Croft, State of Israel Golden Trustee Society, absorption, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Plaque plate - "Louis Croft for Meritorious Service as President, 14th annual Alfred's Charity Dinner", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Citations acknowledging 50 years of service with B'nai B'rith International, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Books/Scrapbooks
  - Ida Kaplan Croft's scrapbook, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ida Kaplan's San Jacinto High School yearbook, "El Orso", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ida Kaplan Croft's high school memory book, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - B'nai B'rith ritual book, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Herzl Lodge Fifty Years of Service in B'nai B'rith memory book, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Memory book from Abe Croft's memorial service, 1972-12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Mizrachi Women yearbook, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Event Invitations, 1944-1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Louis Croft's journal, 1945-06-1945-07 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - To/from Louis Croft, 1940-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - To/from Herzl Lodge #608, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter to Pearl Croft from Senator Ralph Yarborough, 1969-07 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Joint letter to the Adath Yeshurun family in the Armed Forces from Rabbi Tofield (2), 1944-04-1944-05 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Ida Kaplan Croft to Louis Croft during WW II, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letter to Ida Kaplan Croft, 1951-02-17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter to Rochelle Croft from Rabbi William Malev, 1970-01-29 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Event materials
  - B'nai B'rith event programs, 1956-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Program for Third Annual Sweetheart Dance, "Our Candle of Understanding" - Honoring Miss Rochelle Croft, 1966-03-26 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - B'nail B'rith annual Charity Dinner programs, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tribute booklet in memory of Mel Lustgarten, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Program, Houston Jewish Sports Hall of Fame Inaugural Induction - Abe Croft honoree, 1995-05-21 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series V: Financial Materials
  - Invoices, 1943-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series VI: Marketing Material
  - "This is B'nai B'rith Houston pamphlet, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series VII: Meeting Materials
  - Herzl Lodge #608 meeting minutes, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Poem by Abram Geller, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Houston area Men's B'nai B'rith Council, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series VIII: Memorabilia
  - Louis Croft's military materials, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Abe Croft obituary bookmark, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series IX: News Clippings
  - Ida & Louis Croft news clippings, 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photocopied news clippings from Houston Chronicle celebrating V-J Day, 1945-05-15 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Wunsch news clippings, 1973-1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Abe Croft news clippings, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series X: Newsletters
  - Beth El Bulletin, 1944-05 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Sentinel - Jewish Home for the Aged, 1975-06-1977-08 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Herzl-Lite newsletter, 1982-05-1991-11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Gesrei newsletter, Houston Memorial Lodge, B'nai B'rith No. 434, 1985-01 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Herzl Lodge No. 608, 1985-03-1991-07 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series XII: Photographic Materials
  - Photographs, 1934-1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Abe Croft, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - J.C.C. Early Birds, 1966-11-09 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Event photo album/scrapbook, 1971-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographic negatives, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Herzl Lodge photo album, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Croft photo album (events), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series XIII: Speeches
  - Louis Croft's speeches, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series XI: Oversized materials
  - Plaque - B'nai B'rith Youth Services Appeal (Louis Croft), n.d. (Box 4)
  - Retention Award (Louis Croft), 1986 (Box 4)
  - Promotion to high school certificate (Louis Croft), 1931-05-29 (Box 4)
  - Ronnie Arrow Jewish Sports Hall of Fame Award (Abe Croft), 2000-06-11 (Box 4)
  - Promotion to high school certificate (Abe Croft), 1934-05-25 (Box 4)
  - Trophy - Barbara Nathan Carsch Award presented to Rochelle Croft, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Plaque - B'nai B'rith Youth Services Appeal (Ida Croft), n.d. (Box 4)
  - Jewish National Fund Tree certificate presented to Herzl Lodge #608, 1982-03 (Box 4)
  - Archibald A. Mary award presented to Herzl Lodge #608, 1948-04-15 (Box 4)
  - Herzl Lodge Unit No. 608 Charter (2), 1989-01-01 (Box 4)
  - Laminated copies of Herzl Lodge No. 608 Charter (2), 1989-01-01 (Box 4)
  - Abe Croft - group photograph of All Star Football Squad, 1944 (Box 4)
  - JCC Early Birds T-shirt (Louis Croft), n.d. (Box 4)
  - Arabia Shriners hat, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Abe Croft's "All-American 1944" blanket (Box 5)
  - Panoramic Photograph: Bellaire High School graduating class, 1966 (Drawer 189, Folder 1)